# **GUY MBEREBE GUIDONA**

Nationality: Cameroonian | Gender: Male | Phone number: (+1) 4387656554 (Mobile) | Email address:

mguidona@gmail.com | **Twitter:** twitter.com/GMGuidona | **LinkedIn:** linkedin.com/in/guy-guidona

Whatsapp Messenger: +237672301527

Address: 9431 boulevard LaSalle, 104, H8R2M8, Montreal, Canada (Home)

#### About me:

I am a talented, ambitious and hardworking person, with broad skills and experience in software engineering, entrepreneurship and volunteering. Furthermore, I am adept at handling multiple tasks on a daily basis competently and at working well under pressure. A key strength is communication; building strong relationships with people in order to deliver the best results.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

05/10/2022 - CURRENT Montreal, Canada

**SENIOR SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT CONSULTANT ISCI INC.** 

17/11/2019 - 04/10/2022 Yaoundé, Cameroon

**SOFTWARE DEVELOPER SPRINT - PAY CAMEROON SA** 

#### **General description**

- Improve system quality by identifying issues and common patterns, and developing standard operating procedures
- Enhancing applications by identifying opportunities for improvement, making recommendations, designing and implementing systems
- · Maintaining and improving existing code bases and peer review code changes
- Liaising with colleagues to implement technical designs
- Investigating and using new technologies where relevant
- Provide written knowledge transfer material

# Development of a web and desktop platform allowing the Office du Baccalauréat Cameroon (OBC) to centralise all examination management operations Context

In order to facilitate and centralise the management process of the Baccalaureate and Probatoire examinations in Cameroon, the OBC called upon Sprint Pay to design and implement a web and offline platform, allowing them to manage the entire life cycle of official examinations, i.e. from the registration of candidates to the announcement of results.

#### Online at https://www.epimexam.cm

#### Tasks carried out

- Implementation of the core business logic of the application;
- Microservices deployment with service containerization and orchestration;
- SCRUM methodology;
- Data engineering and pipeline definition for data ingestion.

### **Technical environment**

- Programming languages: Java;
- · Frameworks: Spring;
- · Deployment: Docker, Kubernetes;
- Database: MySQL, Elasticsearch;
- Documentation: Swagger, Spring Rest Docs.

# **Sprint Pay payment API**

#### . Context

In an effort to address interoperability issues with money transfers, Sprint Pay has decided to offer the general public a wallet that allows them to to make transactions worldwide without commission.

### **Tasks performed**

· Analysis, design and modeling

- Implementation of micro services for managing payment requests for various payment providers with the development of REST APIs and payment integrations
- · Documentation of APIs
- SCRUM Methodology

#### **Technical environment**

- Programming languages: Java
- · Frameworks: Spring
- Dependency management: Apache Maven
- Testing: JUnit, SonarQube
- Integrated Development Environment: Intelli] IDEA
- Technologies: HTTP, Rest, SOAP, WebSockets
- Documentation: Swagger, Spring Rest Docs

# Development of a web application enabling the Ministry of Finance (MINFI) of Cameroon to Cameroon to follow up on its litigations

Every year, MINFI loses a great deal of money due to poor management of its litigation. It is in this spirit that we have been asked to develop a to develop a litigation management solution for the Ministry.

#### Online at <a href="https://carte-du-contentieux.cm">https://carte-du-contentieux.cm</a>

### Tasks performed

- Backend solution modeling and implementation
- Daily SCRUM meetings, analysis, design and development of microservices for managing document and file storage. Integration of various storage services, APIs and FTP/SFTP servers.

## **Technical environment**

- · Programming languages: Java;
- Frameworks: Spring, Batch programming
- Dependency management: Apache Maven
- Testing: JUnit, SonarQube
- Documentation: Swagger, Spring Rest Docs

**Business or Sector** Financial and insurance activities | **Department** IT

Address Nouvelle Route Omnisport, Yaoundé, Cameroon | Website http://www.sprint-pay.com

04/03/2019 - 02/09/2019 Yaoundé, Cameroon

#### **SOFTWARE DEVELOPER 12S**

## Tasks carried out

## Design and implementation of an Electronic Archives Management System

Design and analysis, writing of functional and technical specifications, development of micro-services, management of the core business, management of clients and web with Spring and Spring Boot frameworks, technical documentation, user acceptance testing.

#### **Technical environment**

- Programming languages: Java, Python, JavaScript, LATEX, HTML5, CSS3
- Framework: Spring Boot, Spring MVC, Spring Data, Spring Security, Spring Cloud, Django, Jinja
- Integrated Development Environment: Intelli] IDEA, Visual Studio Code
- Database: MySQL, Apache Solr (for document indexing)
- Architecture: Microservices
- Tools
  - Code generator: JHipster
  - Testing: JUnit, Rest Assured, SonarQube

01/07/2017 - 28/02/2019 Maroua, Cameroon

**SOFTWARE DEVELOPER** TECHNOLOGY AND INNOVATION SUPPORT CENTER OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MAROUA

# Design and implementation of the student marks management platform of the National Advanced School of Engineering of Maroua Context

The National Advanced School of Engineering of Maroua was in need of a platform for managing the entire life cycle of students marks and performance throughout their studies. This included;

- Marks entered by teachers after evaluation;
- · Results publications;
- · Transcripts and testimonials generation.

#### **Realizations**

· Solution modeling and design;

• Implementation of a solution permitting teachers and users of the platform to enter the marks of the students, generate results and transcripts

#### **Technical environment**

- Programming languages: Java, JavaScript, HTML5, CSS3
- Framework: Spring Boot, Spring Framework, AngularJS
- Integrated Development Environment: Intellij IDEA, Visual Studio Code
- Database: PostgreSQL
  Architecture: Monolith
- · Tools:
  - · Dependency management: Apache Maven;
  - Testing: JUnit, Cucumber, Rest Assured, SonarQube;
  - Deployment (DevOps): Jenkins, Git/GitHub, Apache Tomcat

# Design and implementation of a Transparent Authentication System for the users of the Technology and Innovation Support Center Context

The objective of the project was to offer a user friendly authentication system allowing them to easily access the system from their computers as long as they are connected to the center's WiFi.

#### **Technical environment**

- Programming language: Python
- Tools: mitmproxy <a href="https://mitmproxy.org/">https://mitmproxy.org/</a>

#### Other tasks carried out

- Provide technical assistance and support for incoming queries and issues related to computer systems, software, and hardware.
- Maintain daily performance of computer systems.
- Install, modify, and repair computer hardware and software.
- · Clean up computers.

06/07/2015 - 05/08/2015 Garoua, Cameroon

#### **ICT HELP DESK AGENT BRASSERIES DU CAMEROUN**

#### Tasks carried out

- Provide technical assistance and support for incoming queries and issues related to computer systems, software, and hardware.
- Maintain daily performance of computer systems.
- Respond to email messages from customers seeking help.
- Ask questions to determine the nature of the problem.
- · Walk customer through problem-solving process.
- Install, modify, and repair computer hardware and software.
- Clean up computers.
- Run diagnostic programs to resolve problems.
- Resolve technical problems with Local Area Networks (LAN), Wide Area Networks (WAN), and other systems.
- Install computer peripherals for users.
- Follow up with the customer to ensure the issue has been resolved.

Address Garoua, Cameroon

#### EDUCATION AND TRAINING

01/11/2017 - 02/09/2019 Maroua, Cameroon

**MASTERS OF ENGINEERING DEGREE IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING** National Advanced School of Engineering of Maroua

Address Maroua, Cameroon

**Field of study** Software and applications development and analysis , Inter-disciplinary programmes and qualifications involving Information and Communication Technologies (ICTs) , Database and network design and administration

Final grade A-

#### **HUAWEI SEEDS FOR THE FUTURE** Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.

#### Address Shenzhen, China

10/09/2018 - 13/09/2018 Beijing, China

# **CHINESE LANGUAGE & CULTURE EXPERIENCE PROGRAM** Beijing Language and Culture University

#### Address Beijing, China

15/10/2014 - 25/09/2017 Maroua, Cameroon

# **BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING DEGREE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE AND TELECOMMUNICATIONS** Na tional Advanced School of Engineering of Maroua

Address Maroua, Cameroon

**Field of study** Software and applications development and analysis, Inter-disciplinary programmes and qualifications involving Information and Communication Technologies (ICTs)

#### Final grade B

03/09/2007 - 01/08/2012 Maroua, Cameroon

GCE ORDINARY LEVEL Government Bilingual High School Maroua

#### Address Maroua, Cameroon

03/09/2012 - 01/08/2014 Garoua, Cameroon

GCE ADVANCED LEVEL Government Bilingual High School Garoua

Address Garoua, Cameroon

#### LANGUAGE SKILLS

## Other language(s):

	UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING
	Listening	Reading	Spoken production	Spoken interaction	
ENGLISH	C2	C2	C2	C2	C2
FRENCH	C2	C2	C2	C2	C2
FULAH	B2	B2	B1	B1	A1

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user; B1 and B2: Independent user; C1 and C2: Proficient user

#### DIGITAL SKILLS

OS

Ubuntu | Debian | Linux | Windows

#### **Programming**

CC++ Programming | JHipster | Java Programming language | Python | Git | JUnit | Matlab | NodeJS and ExpressJs | Latex | SQL | Web Development HTML 5 CSS JavaScript | Basic knowledge of PHP programming language | RESTful Webservices | JSON | Maven | Spring Boot | Hibernate

#### **Admin services**

Linux Bash | Apache Tomcat | MySQL | Docker Compose | MongoDB | Centrino | PostgreSQL | Dock er | Kubernetes | Nagios | Jenkins

#### Softwares

Microsoft Office Word Excel Access Power Point Outlook | Intellij IDEA | Visual Studio Visual Studio Code

**Management tools** 

Iira | Confluence

#### ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

#### **NETWORKS AND MEMBERSHIPS**

20/10/2020 – CURRENT UNOPS Global Innovation Center, Lund, Sweden UNOPS Global Challenge GIC Alumni

22/09/2018 – CURRENT Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd. Huawei Seeds For The Future Alumni

#### **CONFERENCES AND SEMINARS**

25/10/2019 - 26/10/2019 - UEBC PAE - ESSAMBA, Maroua

**Engaged African youths: The key to a prosperous Africa** 

26/08/2017 – 27/08/2017 – Movement for Defence of Human Rights and Liberty (MDHRL), Maroua **Fundamental data of human rights: Children's rights, women's rights and humanitarian law** 

#### **HONOURS AND AWARDS**

22/09/2018

Huawei Seeds For The Future 2018 - Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd.

02/10/2014

Les Brasseries du Cameroun award of the best result for the 2014 GCE Advanced Level session in the North Region – Les Brasseries du Cameroun Award of the best pupil and result at the 2014 GCE Advanced Level session in the North Region - Cameroon

17/09/2012

**Les Brasseries du Cameroun award of the best result for the 2012 GCE Ordinary Level session in the Far-North Region – Les Brasseries du Cameroun** Award of the best pupil and result at the 2012 GCE Ordinary Level session in the Far North Region - Cameroon

#### **MANAGEMENT AND LEADERSHIP SKILLS**

**Co- Founder & Vice President of Action for Education and Peace** Co-Founder and Vice-President of Action for Education and Peace, an association based in Maroua - Cameroon, composed of young entrepreneurs with aim to promote on the national plan *education*, *entrepreneurship and solidarity* 

#### **HOBBIES AND INTERESTS**

Sports Football, Jogging